Okay Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is ק"ף כ"ף Kuf Chaf 120.
We pick up on קייט עמוד ב, Kuf Yud Tes Amud Bet,
six lines down in the wide lines. אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב
שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda berei de-Rav Shmuel. Thank you Michael for covering
yesterday. We had a whole nice discussion yesterday all about
כבוד שבת, Kavod Shabbos, עונג שבת, Oneg Shabbos, כבוד שבת, Kavod Shabbos,
famous אגדתא Aggadata about יוסף מוקיר שבתא, Yosef Mokir Shabbasa, interesting גמרא
Gemara about not only about how rabbis would personally be very involved
in the act of כבוד שבת, Kavod Shabbos, like an important guest
is coming, you know, the importance of not just having everything ready
but being involved in making ready, also fascinating little discussion about whether
you get dressed up nicely for your preparations or you're supposed to
know dress up in more dirty clothes for your preparations, so even
that's a sort of sign of, you know, appropriate clothing. So that
was interesting about sort of the question of combining dress with the
actual preparations themselves. Anyway, that's the larger context here about eating and
כבוד שבת. Kavod Shabbos. So now we continue, אמר רב יהודה בריה
דרב שמואל משמיה דרב, Amar Rav Yehuda berei de-Rav Shmuel mishmei de-Rav,
אין הדלקה מצויה, ein hadlaka metzuya, now, הדלקה, hadlaka, we actually were
talking, let's remember what got us into this conversation, we were talking
about
if
a fire breaks out on שבת, Shabbos, saving the food for three
meals on שבת. Shabbos. So here there's a tie-in about what, why
would a fire break out? And it also ties in the same
way we had a lot of praises for people that were מכבד,
mekhabed, that did כבוד שבת, Kavod Shabbos, that kept שבת. Shabbos. If
ישראל Yisrael kept two שבתות, Shabbasos, they would, they would immediately get
redeemed. So now we turn to a little bit of a negative
rhetoric about why certain punishments and bad things happen. So, אין הדלקה
מצויה, ein hadlaka metzuya, fire is only prevalent, meaning when a fire
breaks out, במקום שיש חילול שבת, bemakom she-yesh chillul Shabbos, it's a
place where שבת Shabbos is desecrated. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says:
ואם לא תשמעו אלי לקדש את יום השבת ולבלתי שאת משא, Ve-im
lo tishme'u elai lekadesh es yom ha-Shabbos ve-lavitasei masa, if you do
not listen to me to sanctify שבת Shabbos and not to carry,
then והצתי אש בשעריה ואכלה ארמנות ירושלים ולא תכבה, ve-hitzati esh besha'areha
ve-achala armonot Yerushalayim velo tichbe, I will, I will kindle a fire
in its gates and it will eat, it will destroy, it will
consume the palaces of, the towers of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ולא תכבה, velo
tichbe, it will not be extinguished. מאי ולא תכבה? Mai velo tichbe?
What is meant that it will not be extinguished? אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, בשעה שאין בני אדם מצויין
לכבותה, besha'a she-ein bnei adam metzuyin le-chabota, it'll actually happen on a
time when people aren't around to put it out, so that it
will continue to burn. What's a time when people aren't around to
put it out? Presumably שבת. Shabbos. I mean we're actually going to
look about how do you put out a fire on שבת, Shabbat,
but anyway certainly not convenient and maybe you're all in שול. shul.
So that's a little מידה כנגד מידה midda keneged midda for not
keeping
שבת. Shabbat. אמר אביי, Amar Abbaye, לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שחיללו
בה את השבת, lo charva Yerushalayim ella bishvil she-chillalu bah es ha-Shabbos,
so in the similar vein ירושלים Yerushalayim was only destroyed because of
שבת Shabbos was desecrated. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ומשבתותי
העלימו עיניהם, umishabbotosai he'elimu eineihem, from my שבתות shabbasos they closed their
eyes, ואחל בתוכם, ve'achel betocham, and I will, you know, begin in
their midst the destruction. ואחל בתוכם Ve'achel betocham means, I think it
means from להתחיל, le-hatchil, what does it say, no?
No, but in the rest it must be, yeah, the rest the
destruction.
אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, yes?
I have a question, when they say that it's that the fire's
only found in a place where שבת Shabbat is being just desecrated,
are they talking like literal punishment or are they saying people are
desecrating it by lighting fires?
No, no, no, it's a punishment.
It's a punishment.
Yes. Now look, the problem with this is, I should just say
maybe it's obvious, you know, there's one thing about this type of
a rhetoric that makes people feel how serious the sin is and
heightens them to the sensitivity and, you know, hopefully makes them more
observant and so on. The problem is that when this becomes like
a type of an after-the-fact finger pointing, which sometimes is what happens,
like, you know, there's a, you know, something bad happens and some
rabbi gets up, more often happens in Israel than here, but some
rabbi gets up because I said the whole religious, there tends to
be greater extremism there and sort of fundamentalism. Some rabbi gets up
and says, ah, the reason this thing happened or whatever is because
it must be that people weren't being, people weren't keeping שבת Shabbos
well enough, people were מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos and, you know, and
all of that type of finger-pointing which is very much against, you
know, the גמרא Gemara says it explicitly, but you know amongst other
things about the arrogance of thinking about we know how God operates,
but the idea of אונאת דברים, ona'as devarim, that somebody has something
bad happen to them and you increase the sense of, you know,
of tragedy and by blaming them for it and finger-pointing about what
sin caused it, you know, it's a, it's a very pro, it's
deeply problematic. That obviously is not the intent of the גמרא Gemara
here, the גמרא's Gemara using this more as rhetoric to encourage observance.
Yes, Charlie?
But there's a historical problem, at the time the temple was destroyed,
Jews were doing a lot of other bad things, probably weren't even
keeping שבת. Shabbos.
Well okay, so that is true, you know, and there are גמרות
Gemaras that speak about that, about that everybody kept all the מצוות
mitzvos and the whole issue was about what do you call it?
was about like שנאת חינם, sinas chinam, other types of things. Now
here it is also quoting פסוקים pesukim from the נביאים, Nevi'im, so
it's talking about the מקדש ראשון Mikdash Rishon not the מקדש שני,
Mikdash Sheni, not clear if the גמרא Gemara is exactly distinguishing between
the two of those though. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu, לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל...
lo charva Yerushalayim ella bishvil... שביטלו קריאת שמע שחרית וערבית. shebitlu krias
shema shacharis va'arvis. So now pointing it even to more minor sins,
only because they didn't do saying the שמע shema in the morning
and the evenings. שנאמר Shenemar the פסוק pasuk says: הוי משכימי בבוקר
שכר ירדופו, Hoi mashkimei vaboker shechar yirdofu, woe to those who get
up early in the morning and run after a beer, run after
you know mead rather than getting up and saying שמע, Shema, they're
running after their pleasures. וכתיב והיה כינור ונבל ותוף וחליל ויין משתיהם
Uchshiv vehaya kinnor vanevel vetof vechalil veyayin mishtehem and they you know
they had all these various instruments that they at when they were
in their drinking of wine and they're playing of music. ואת פועל
השם לא יביטו Ve'et poal Hashem lo yabitu and they do not
look at the actions of God you know because שמע'ס Shema's also
about מעשה בראשית, ma'aseh bereishis, it's the ברכות brachos in the morning
associated with שמע Shema about God creating the world and יוצר המאורות.
Yotzer HaMe'oros. So instead they're running after all these pleasures and not
being sensitive to God in the world which is part of the
שמע. Shema. וכתיב לכן גלה עמי מבלי דעת Uchshiv lachen gala ami
mibli da'at and therefore my people is exiled without you know without
knowledge without this awareness. Okay so רש"י Rashi says they didn't see
God's actions in order to be מייחד שמו meyached shemo to say
like because the end of the פסוק pasuk is because yeah so
that's what רש"י Rashi says, it's מייחד שמו meyached shemo specifically about
like השם אחד. Hashem Echad. But I think it's not just about
declaring God's name but sort of seeing God in the world. Okay
and you know the point here might be actually because this is
you know about here as opposed to the שבת Shabbat point, here
the point might be exactly that that like before you focus on
the bigger sins it's important to point to what are the sort
of smaller mistakes maybe in terms of their הלכתי halakhic weight but
smaller that's central to the whole religious experience and the whole way
of looking at the world that ultimately cultivates and leads to you
know the bigger problems is because it starts with a lack of
that fundamental that bedrock of seeing God in the world, believing in
God, the sensitivity to God and so on. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב המנונא לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שביטלו
בה תינוקות של בית רבן. Amar Rav Hamnuna lo charva Yerushalayim ela
bishvil shebitlu bah tinokos shel beis rabban. The reason ירושלים Yerushalayim was
destroyed was because they prevented because the the school children you know
who went to חדר cheder religious school you know were you know
they they wasted their time they did not you know they prevented
them from going to school. שנאמר Shenemar the verse says: שפוך על
עולל בחוץ, Shefoch al olel bachutz, pour down onto the you know
the suckling, the infant outdoors. מה טעם שפוך? Ma ta'am shefoch? Why
is it poured down the wrath, you know why is ירושלים Yerushalayim
destroyed? משום דעולל בחוץ Mishum de'olel bachutz because the kids are outside
and they're not in school where they should be. Right, you know
have you seen that whole new ad series? You know it says
like "It's 9:00 AM, do you know where your kids are?" So
that's the point, you know are the kids in school like they
should be? And I would say it's a similar issue here, you
know it's that
maybe you're good at observance
and
maybe whatever but you know
you don't care enough about it to ensure that you're educating the
next generation sufficiently. And you know and therefore in that's you know
all these smaller things are indicative of a lack of a type
of a of a of a fundamental concern about the importance of
it, the continuity of it, the sensitivity to this whole type of
a religious thing and of a you know of a religious outlook
and ultimately that is you know that leads to all these other
things. Yes.
It was late in בית שני Bayis Sheni times that בן גמלא
Ben Gamla put in the גזירה gezeirah that everybody...
Yeah yeah it's a question about whether the גמרא Gemara is reading
this in the through the lens of בית ראשון Bayis Rishon or
בית שני Bayis Sheni although the פסוקים pesukim are for בית ראשון.
Bayis Rishon. Okay. אמר עולא לא חרבה ירושלים אלא מפני שלא היה
להם בושת פנים Amar Ulla lo charva Yerushalayim ela mipnei shelo haya
lahem boshes panim because they did not have shame. זה מזה ze
mizeh
embarrassment from one to the other for acting incorrectly. שנאמר הובישו כי
תועבה עשו, Shenemar hovishu ki to'eva asu, you should be embarrassed, shame
because you have done an abomination. גם בוש לא יבושו gam bosh
lo yevoshu but they are not embarrassed. Okay so again if you
don't have a basic type of a shame for acting incorrectly you
know then thank you then that means that you do not that
you go ahead and you do the types of things you should
not be doing. So again what I see as the common denominator
about all these things is not that there was a terrible sin
in the thing itself but that this type of a of a
character, of an attitude, of a way of being in the world
ultimately leads to a real loosening of one's inherent adherence of opening
the door for you know for sin and so on. So it's
more the sort of the deeper sources of where all the other
problems stem from.
Okay. אמר רב יצחק לא
חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שהושוו קטן וגדול Amar Rav Yitzchak lo charva
Yerushalayim ela bishvil shehushvu katan vegadol because they equated the small with
the great meaning they didn't understand you know you know the difference
about people's stature and and and appropriately honor and respect it. שנאמר
והיה כעם ככהן, Shenemar vehaya kha'am kakhohen, the people were like the
כהן, kohen, you know there's no difference between the laity and the
religious leadership, everybody was total equality you know not even meritocracy.
וכתיב ואחריו הבוק תבוק. Uchshiv ve'acharav habok tibok. אמר רב עמרם בריה
דרבי שמעון בר אבא, Amar Rav Amram breih d'Rabbi Shimon bar Abba,
אמר רבי שמעון בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Shimon bar Abba, אמר רבי
חנינא: Amar Rabbi Chanina: לא חרבה ירושלים, Lo charva Yerushalayim, Jerusalem was
only destroyed, אלא בשביל שלא הוכיחו זה את זה, ella bishvil shelo
hochichu ze es ze, because they did not remonstrate, give תוכחה tochacha
to one another. Again, so, you know, that becomes then a, if
you don't tell people you're doing something wrong, A, you lose your
own sensitivity to it, they lose their sensitivity, and B, you know,
it's giving a silent condoning of other people's activities. So again, it's
all these all fall the pattern that these are the types of
sins that lead to more fundamental, you know, sinning and violation. שנאמר,
Shene'emar, as the verse says, היו שריה כאיילים לא מצאו מרעה. hayu
sareha k'ayalim lo matzu mir'eh. Its officers were like deers, not אילים.
eylim. What's an איל? ayil? אייל, ayal, אייל? ayal? Yeah, what's אילים?
eylim? אילים's eylim a ram. Rams, so I guess rams, right, right,
or harts. Okay, they were like rams that did not find grazing.
מה אייל זה ראשו של זה בצד זנבו של זה, Ma ayal
ze rosho shel ze b'tzad zanavo shel ze, the same way when
rams go out, one head is towards the tail of the other,
אף ישראל שבאותו דור כבשו פניהם בקרקע, af Yisrael sheb'oso dor kavshu
pneihem bakarka, so similarly like, you know, like what, if they're grazing
and all their heads are down, so in that generation everybody buried
their head in the ground, did not look one another in the
face, just buried their, put their, you know, buried their head in
the sand, ולא הוכיחו זה את זה, v'lo hochichu ze es ze,
did not remonstrate and that ultimately led to greater sin and violation.
אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שביזו
בה תלמידי חכמים, lo charva Yerushalayim ella bishvil shebizu bah talmidei chachamim,
similar to the idea of equating the small and the great, they
did not show respect for תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, Torah sages or
Torah students of Torah and ultimately that led to a denigration of
Torah and the authority of Torah, שנאמר shene'emar is the פסוק pasuk
says, ויהיו מלעיבים במלאכי האלוהים, v'yihyu mal'ivim b'mal'achei ha'elokim, and they would
cause, you know, pain, suffering to to the angels of God, ובוזים
דבריו, u'vozim d'varav, and they would denigrate his words, ומתעתעים בנביאיו, u'misa'ta'im
binvi'av, and they would mock God's, God's God's prophets, עד עלות חמת
השם בעמו, ad alot chamat Hashem b'amo, until the anger of God
rise up against his nation, עד לאין מרפא ad le'ein marpe until
there was no healing. מאי עד לאין מרפא? Mai ad le'ein marpe?
What does it mean no healing? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, כל המבזה תלמיד חכם אין לו רפואה למכתו.
kol hamivaze talmid chacham ein lo refuah l'makato. Okay, so not something,
you know, pretty much just the straight explanation based on the previous
explanation. Anybody who denigrates a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, the wound that
they deserve will, that they will get will have no healing. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai
d'chsiv, what is meant by אל תגעו במשיחי ובנביאי אל תרעו, al
tigu vimshichai uvinvi'ai al tare'u, do not touch my anointed ones and
do not do evil to my prophet. אל תגעו במשיחי, Al tigu
vimshichai, do not touch my anointed ones, אלו תינוקות של בית רבן,
elu tinokos shel beis raban, these are the the schoolchildren of their
master's home, meaning that you have to don't sort of mess with
them, don't take them out of school, don't interfere, you have to
make sure that the kids are getting a good Jewish education.
Well plus also back then they used to especially think that oil
was very helpful for, for people, especially the kids.
Right, so thank you. So רש"י Rashi says that, that they would
part of sort of the way, you know, that the education as
well, they would like put oil on the heads of the school
kids. ובנביאי אל תרעו, Uvinvi'ai al tare'u, and you do not do
evil with my prophet, אלו תלמידי חכמים, elu talmidei chachamim, the תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim, so picking up the themes we mentioned before about
both respect for the Torah sages and students and when they get
to a certain level, but also the investment at the youth in
making sure that they're getting even as young kids, as kindergarten kids
are getting, they're getting the type of education that they need. All
of this ultimately is showing the importance and respect of Torah, which,
you know, if you don't have that then it undermines the whole
life of observance. אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיאה, Amar Reish
Lakish mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, Reish Lakish in the name of Rabbi
Yehuda Nesi'ah, not Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah which was the
grandson of Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi, אין
עולם מתקיים אלא בשביל הבל תינוקות של בית רבן. ein olam miskayem
ella bishvil hevel tinokos shel beis raban. The world only exists because
of the breath of the, of, from, from the mouths of school
children, you know, from the innocent learning of words of the school
children. So אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Papa l'Abaye,
so now that's one end of the extreme, before we mentioned תלמידי
חכמים. talmidei chachamim. So Rav Papa said to Abaye, דידי ודידך מאי?
didi v'didach mai? What about our Torah learning? What, that doesn't help
the world spin on its axis? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said to him, אינו דומה הבל שיש בו חטא להבל שאין בו
חטא. eino domeh hevel sheyesh bo cheit l'hevel she'ein bo cheit. Breath
that is with sin is not the same as breath that is
without sin. There's the innocence of their learning and it's pure learning
of Torah and these are people that have never, you know, kids,
never done anything wrong, and there's a purity to that that ultimately
is sort of sustains the world. So there's something very beautiful about
that. It's not just the intellectual achievement, but there's something about innocence
and purity that ultimately, you know, gives the world future hope and
sustains the world. ואמר ריש לקיש, V'amar Reish Lakish, and said Reish
Lakish, משום רבי יהודה נשיאה, mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesi'ah, אין מבטלין תינוקות
של בית רבן אפילו לבניין בית המקדש. ein mivatlin tinokos shel beis
raban afilu l'vinyan beis hamikdash. You do not take kids out of,
out of school except for the building of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. That and Presidents' Day. Okay, אפילו, afilu, even, excuse me, I
said, I said except, I'm sorry, even, even for the building of
the. I know. Actually, if you see of all the things we're
saying that until now has been more rhetoric, you know, whatever, דרשה,
drasha, there's a little letter by that, the רמב"ם Rambam actually brings
this down as a הלכה, halacha, you know, in הלכות תלמוד תורה,
Hilchos Talmud Torah, you know, basically says that it's so important that
even for the purpose, even if the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
being built, the kids would be staying in school. Okay. So, what?
אפילו לבנין של בית המקדש. afilu livinyan shel Beit HaMikdash. ואמר ריש
לקיש Ve'amar Reish Lakish משום רבי יהודה נשיאה, mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesia,
כך מקובלני מאבותי, kach mikublani me'avotai, here's what I have, so ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish said to רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, here's
my tradition I have from my forefathers. ואמרי לה, Ve'amri lah, some
say מאבותיך, me'avotecha, he said it's from your forefathers, presumably like רבי
יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. כל עיר שאין בה תינוקות של בית
רבן, kol ir she'ein bah tinokot shel beit raban, any city that
does not have in it school children, like so there's not a
חדר, cheder, you know, a Jewish school set up in a city,
מחריבין אותה, machrivin otah, it gets destroyed. It won't last. So רבינא
Ravina אמר amar מחרימין אותה, machrimin otah, חרם, cherem, which is worse
than מחריב, machriv, מחרימין machrimin is like a complete destruction. ואמר רבא,
Ve'amar Rava, and רבא Rava said, לא חרבה ירושלים אלא בשביל שפסקו
ממנה אנשי אמנה. lo charva Yerushalayim ela bishvil shepasku mimena anshei amana.
So now moving from the תורה Torah and the investment in תורה
Torah and הוכחה hochacha and so on, we get more to I
think a general statement about morality and faithfulness. The reason ירושלים Yerushalayim
was destroyed was because people that were of that were trustworthy, of
integrity, ceased from ירושלים. Yerushalayim. שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, שוטטו
בחוצות ירושלים וראו נא, shotetu bechutzot Yerushalayim ure'u na, spread out through
the through the, you know, what do you call it, the the
the open places, the markets of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and go see, ודעו
ובקשו ברחובותיה, ude'u uvakshu birchovoteha,
go you know, seek out in its in its in its streets,
אם תמצאו איש עשה משפט, im timtze'u ish oseh mishpat, do you
can you find anybody who is doing justice? מבקש אמונה, mevakesh emunah,
looking for truthfulness, for faithfulness. ואסלח לה, ve'eslach lah, and then I
will forgive it. But because you couldn't find, you know, one trustworthy
person, it was destroyed. So again, an interesting shift moving you know,
from again, from issues around תורה Torah and תורה Torah authority and
respect for תורה Torah and so on, to this issue about that
gets back to the how we began this discussion about שומר אמונים,
shomer emunim, right, a גוי goy who keeps the faith and keeps
אמן, Amen, and here it's about trustworthiness. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says, איני, eini, is that really true? ואמר רב קטינא, Ve'amar Rav
Ketina, אפילו בשעת כשלונה של ירושלים, afilu besha'at kishlonah shel Yerushalayim, even
in the times of the stumbling of ירושלים Yerushalayim and when it
was sinning and deserving of punishment, לא פסקו ממנה אנשי אמנה, lo
pasku mimena anshei amana, people of faith and trustworthiness did not cease.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, כי יתפש איש באחיו בית אביו,
ki yitpos ish be'achiv beit aviv, one person will grab in his
you know his brother from his father's house,
שמלה לכה קצין תהיה לנו, simlah lecha katzin tihyeh lanu, come, you
should be the ruler over us. So what does that mean? It
means, דברים שבני אדם מתכסים בהם כשמלה, devarim shevnei adam mitkasim bahem
kesimlah, so things that people wrap amongst themselves like a garment, which
is you know,
you know, that sort of like they they hide, they pretend like
that they don't have this thing. ישנן בידך, yeshnan beyadecha, you have
this, you have like this תורה Torah knowledge, you should be a
an authority over us. Okay. והמכשלה הזאת תחת ידך, vehamachshelah hazot tachat
yadecha, and this stumbling is under your hand, what does that mean?
דברים שאין בני אדם עומדים עליהם אלא אם כן נכשלים בהם, devarim
she'ein bnei adam omdim aleihem ela im ken nichshalim bahem, types of
things that are so difficult that people you know from that don't
really learn them until they make mistakes, like a lot of the
things you can't grasp right away and you have to learn it
and make mistakes and learn it again, and sometimes it actually means
you have to act you act incorrectly and you learn from from
the mistakes that you've made. So these types of things that are
really hard to know and acquire, ישנן תחת ידך, yeshnan tachat yadecha,
they're saying you've got this, you have תורה, Torah, the things that
most people hide, you have things that people that most that you
don't have people don't know until they make mistakes about, you know,
you have this difficult knowledge, you you really know תורה. Torah. So
one minute, תהיה לנו, tihyeh lanu, so they'll say to this person,
be a ruler over us, you are a big תלמיד חכם. talmid
chacham. So and what does he say back? ישא ביום ההוא לאמר
לא אהיה חובש, yisa bayom hahu le'emor lo eheyeh chovesh, he will
take an oath on that day saying, I will not be חובש,
chovesh, which we'll see how the גמרא Gemara interprets it, bound or
something. So אין ישא אלא לשון שבועה, ein yisa ela leshon shevuah,
ישא yisa means to take an oath. וכן הוא אומר, vechen hu
omer, and it says, לא תשא את שם ה' אלהיך, lo tisa
et shem Hashem Elokecha, right, do not take God's name. לא אהיה
חובש, lo eheyeh chovesh, so what how he'll respond to this demand
that he should be a ruler because he's a big תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, he'll respond by saying, לא אהיה מחובשי עצמן בבית המדרש.
lo eheyeh mechovshei atzman bebeit hamidrash.
I will not be by or I will not be, right he
says it means I am not of, although it's the language is
a little more involved, I am not amongst those people that bind
themselves in the בית מדרש. beit medrash. You're making a mistake, guys.
I'm not a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, I'm not the guy that
like straps himself to his chair and, you know, knows you know,
learned a lot of תורה. Torah. Don't don't be fooled. Okay. ובביתי
אין לחם ואין שמלה, uvveiti ein lechem ve'ein simlah, in my house
there's no bread and there's no cloak. שאין בידי לא מקרא ולא
משנה, she'ein beyadi lo mikra velo mishnah, I don't have any of
the things you think I have, I don't have
bread. the basic,
the most fundamental aspects of תורה, Torah, like I don't know פסוקים
psukim and I don't have like this garment you say, I don't
have משנה mishna ולא גמרא, velo Gemara, I don't know גמרא. Gemara.
So I don't know any of this stuff. You're making a mistake,
don't have me. Anyway, so the point of this whole דרשה drasha
is, is that look, people are at least honest. Here's this guy
they want him to be their head, and they think he's a
big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, presumably he has some תורה Torah knowledge.
But he's saying, no, you're making a mistake, I'm not the guy
you're looking for, I'm not the person who has this type of
learning. So you see that even at this time that they still
had people that are honest and are trustworthy. So the גמרא Gemara
says: וממאי, Umimai, how do you know that's what that proves? דילמא
שאני התם דאי אמרו ליה גמירנא
אמרו ליה אימא לן. Dilma shani hasam di amru leh gmirna amru
leh eima lan. So maybe there's other reasons for not lying. Maybe
not because you're truthful, but if he says, yeah, you're right, I
am a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, then they'll say, great, now give
a גמרא Gemara שיעור. shiur. Okay, so maybe he's not lying just
because he's honest, I mean maybe he's not telling the truth because
he wants to be honest, but because he doesn't want to get
in a position that he can't handle. So the גמרא Gemara says:
No, הוה
ליה למימר, hava leh lemeimar, if he was more concerned about his
image and not about the truth, what he should have said was,
גמר ושכח. gmar vshachach. You're right, I used to be a תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham, but you know what, it's been a long time,
I've forgotten some of it and so on. Then he would have
got out of the demands and he wouldn't have had to be
honest that he never had any תורה Torah knowledge. And the fact
that he's saying I never have had any תורה Torah knowledge shows
that at least he was honest. Okay, מאי לא היה חובש כלל?
mai lo hayah chovesh klal? Why is he saying that I was
never amongst the people that was in the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash?
So anyway, so what's the upshot of all of this? So how
can you say that ירושלים Yerushalayim was destroyed because people of trustworthiness
ceased? See, here you see that here's somebody that even though is
at least he's honest, whatever else is true you could say about
him, at least he's being honest. So גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בדברי תורה כאן במשא ומתן. Kan
b'divrei Torah kan b'masa u'matan. Question is about whether תורה Torah or
whether about business. By תורה, Torah, maybe at least that's the one
thing that people weren't gonna lie about. Maybe they had enough respect
for תורה Torah that they weren't gonna lie about their תורה Torah
knowledge. Business, where also there's a bigger יצר הרע yetzer hara maybe,
business when people stop being honest about business, that's when ירושלים Yerushalayim
was destroyed. Okay, so anyway the interesting upshot about this is while
it starts with a big emphasis of ירושלים Yerushalayim being destroyed because
of issues around observance and respect for תורה, Torah, in the end
what it says is that even when it was destroyed, there was
still enough respect for תורה Torah that people wouldn't lie about that,
but in the end it was destroyed because of a basic loss
of fundamental morality and people not being honest in their business dealings.
Okay, so that was a whole fascinating series of דרשות drashot starting
about כבוד ועונג שבת, kavod ve'oneg Shabbos, transferring into a discussion about
the bad things if you don't keep שבת Shabbos and then why
ירושלים Yerushalayim was destroyed, a whole list of things, which again, this
is more interesting as opposed to other places where things about גילוי
עריות, gilei arayot, שפיכות דמים, shfichus damim, and so on. Here it
talks about more characterological or sociological things that led to undermining commitment
in observance. Yes, Michael?
I don't know if you were able to or playing on it,
you mentioned at some point you're going to try to talk about
some of the actual הלכות. halachot.
Oh,
okay, so I haven't had a chance, so hopefully I'll try to
get back to you on that. Okay, so let's take a look
now as we go from, we continue in the theme about saving
food, but we move from the issue about three meals to other
specifics about saving food. מצילים סל מלא ככרות אף על פי שיש
בה מאה סעודות. Matzilim sal malei kikarot af al pi sheyesh bah
meah seudos.
If you have one basket, although we said three meals, if you
have a single basket that has in it a hundred loaves of
bread, you can save the whole basket. Presumably because it's one action
of picking up the basket. So you don't have to take bread
out of it to save less than three foods.
Small one big one, does it make a difference?
Well, we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. ועיגול של דבילה, Ve’igul shel
dveilah, or let's say this
big clump of pressed dates, even though it's bigger than three meals'
worth because it's like one object. וחבית של יין, Vechavis shel yayin,
or a barrel of wine, same basic point, you can take one
object even if it has many meals' worth of food in it.
ואומר לאחרים, V’omer la’acherim, that's one way in which you can save
more. And here's another way you can save more. You can say
to other people: בואו והצילו לכם. bo’u vehatzilu lachem. My house is
burning down, I can only save three meals, if anybody wants free
food, come and save for yourself. So then I'm not saving for
me, people are taking for themselves. Okay, and therefore it's allowed for
each person to take even though it's not their food, to take
three meals for him or herself.
Because I mean they have their own
food, so why,
yeah, it's a good question. It's חז"ל Chazal sort of balancing, it's
a very good question, meaning if they don't need it, I mean
you would think that this is consistent maybe with the position of
who was it רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose before that said whatever time
the fire broke out you could always save three. So that becomes
like a type of a לא פלוג. lo plug. But according to
the rabbis that say well depends night or day or afternoon, so
yeah why are other people allowed to as well? It's a good
question. You know, although look, even when I'm allowed to save, they
didn't say well if you've got food if you're invited to somebody
else's house or if you have food stored... stored in another house,
you're not allowed to save, so, you know, anyway, so, okay, these
are people, but it is a good question. Obviously they're trying to
strike a balance between not letting the you going overboard and leading
to you putting out of fire and on the other hand trying
to give you ways with restrictions and rules that you can still
salvage as much as possible. Okay, so then they're saving for themselves.
אם היו פקחין עושים עמהם חשבון אחר שבת. Im hayu pikchin osin
imahem cheshbon achar shabbat. If they're smart, then after שבת Shabbat they'll
make a, you know, they'll figure out the, you know,
the account, meaning they'll somehow figure out a way in which he'll
get his food back and they'll get paid for their effort. Okay,
we'll discuss that in the גמרא. Gemara.
חשבון Cheshbon is like, you know, the computations.
Okay, settling of accounts.
Settling of accounts, thanks. לאיכן
מצילין, Le-heichan metzilin, now, similar to the discussion before about ספרי קודש
Sifrei Kodesh where that you could save it to where, and there
it was into a certain type of a חצר chatzer that did
not have all of the necessary
architectural aspects to allow carrying in it, like maybe it didn't have
the, you know, according to an opinion that you needed two posts
and it only had one post. There was something that wasn't architecturally
complete there, and nevertheless, there was an allowance. Here by food, we're
not as lenient. The courtyard has to be completely with all the
posts and everything. So where you save it to? לחצר מעורבת. Le-chatzer
me'urevet. And not only does it have to have all the posts,
you have to have made an עירוב. eiruv. It has to be
totally permissible to carry in. We're not making any allowances. Okay. בן
בתירא אומר, Ben Beteira omer, בן בתירא Ben Beteira is a more
lenient. אף לשאינה מעורבת, Af le-she-eina me'urevet, as long as the courtyard
is architecturally correct, even without an עירוב, eiruv, we will allow you
to save. But again, according to the rabbis, we're actually, by the
ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, there was a leniency. Even though there was
a slight problem of carrying, we allowed you to do it for
the sake of saving ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. Here by the food,
it's a stringency. There's no problem of carrying, the courtyard has an
עירוב, eiruv, the whole thing, and even so, we want to limit
the amount of food you carry. We're being strict, not lenient, because
if you do too much, it'll come, the concern was to putting
out the fire.
Okay,
this makes it quite
clear, even more extreme, that it's not, there's no pretense that they're
doing it really for themselves,
or they're giving it to them, like they, it implies that they're
doing it for
the בעל הבית.
ba'al ha-bayit. Well, the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say that about that
it's, the reason it says פקחין, pikchin, it's all like a הערמה,
ha'arama, like ostensibly I'm saying save it for yourself, but it's all
with a wink and a nod and we all know that after
שבת, Shabbat, you'll, if you're, you'll give it back to me and
I'll pay you for your efforts. So that's the way the גמרא
Gemara interprets it. We'll see how it gets dealt with in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So now we move on from food to clothes.
ולשם מוציא כלי תשמישו, U-le-sham motzi k'lei tashmisho, there you can bring
out, now what we do allow you is to take out the
objects that you need, like, now again, it doesn't mean like all
of your stuff, but רש"י Rashi says things you'll need for שבת,
Shabbat, like, you know, table, chairs, whatever.
So exactly how you draw the limit of what you need on
שבת Shabbat or not, like,
but okay. ולובש כל מה שיוכל ללבוש. U-lovesh kol mah she-yuchal lilbosh.
And by clothing, rather than saying what you normally would wear or
x amount of clothes, we said anything that it's possible to wear,
you know, put as much clothes on your back whatever you and
walk out with them. All this is while the fire's raging. ועוטף
כל מה שיוכל לעטוף. Ve-otef kol mah she-yuchal la'atof.
And you wrap like on yourself like, you know, like an outer
garment, anything you can wrap on yourself. So anything you can carry
out on your back in terms of clothing you're allowed.
Could you go back and forth?
We'll talk about that in a minute. רבי יוסי אומר י"ח כלים.
Rabbi Yose omer yod-chet keilim. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says no, not
anything, only your standard 18 garments. We'll list what those standard 18
garments are in the גמרא. Gemara.
וחוזר ולובש ומוציא. Ve-chozer ve-lovesh u-motzi. And back presumably not רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, back to the חכמים, Chachamim, you can go, you know,
put tons of clothes on your back, take it out, take it
all off, go back and get dressed again with a ton of
clothes. So as opposed, interestingly, as opposed to food, you know, where
it was three, here they defined it by anything you can wear,
but a similar to like the food, then they had loopholes to
that, like come and take as much, you know, food for yourself.
Here they say go back and, you know, wear out more and
more clothes. Presumably if you're wearing it out, it's less like you're
carrying it out, although the problem here isn't a carrying concern because
it is to a חצר chatzer with an עירוב. eiruv. ואומר לאחרים
בואו והצילו עמי. Ve-omer le-acherim bo'u ve-hatzilu imi. And here also you
can say to people, 'Come help me.' Now the גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to say, going back to דב'ס Dov's point, how come here it
says 'Come help me,' which makes it obvious that you're doing it
for me, and how come before it was 'Come save for yourself'?
So we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara.
גמרא Gemara says, והתניא רישא ג' סעודות. Ve-ha-tanya reisha gimel se'udot. So
it asks the question, how could you say you can take a
basket filled with bread? Don't we say in the earlier משנה Mishnah
three meals? The answer seems obvious. ותו לא, Ve-tu lo, and no
more. אמר רב הונא לא קשיא. Amar Rav Huna la kashya. It's
not difficult. כאן בבא להציל כאן בבא לקפל. Kan be-ba le-hatzil kan
be-ba le-kapel. This question is, it's a funny phrase what the גמרא
Gemara uses to describe the difference. Are you coming to save, or
are you coming to double up? So, you know, bundle up. Meaning,
if it's one object like a big basket filled with bread or
a barrel filled with wine, that's fine. If you're coming to, you
know, to double up, to bundle up, like take multiple baskets, multiple
loaves of bread and each one is a separate... separate עסק, esek,
then you're limited to three meals' worth. Okay, בא להציל מציל את
כולם, Ba lehatzil matzil et kulam, if you're coming to save. Again,
it's funny why that's the word להציל lehatzil here means that, but
this is what רש"י Rashi says and that's clearly the most obvious
difference between the משניות. Mishnayot. If you're coming to save, meaning in
one take one object, so you can take even all of the
all of the loaves in the basket. בא לקפל Ba lekapel if
you're coming to, you know, to collect multiple baskets or multiple loaves,
אין מקפל אלא מזון ג' סעודות, ein mekapel ela mazon gimel sudot,
you're limited to three meals. רב אבא בר זבדא אמר אמר רב,
Rav Abba bar Zavda amar amar Rav, so רב אבא בר זבדא
Rav Abba bar Zavda said in the name of רב, Rav, אידי
ואידי בבא לקפל. idi ve'idi be'ba lekapel. No, even our משנה Mishna
could be when you're coming to like gather together. So basically you've
got one basket, maybe it's empty, you don't it's not already filled
with loaves of bread, and you can still put tons of bread
in it. Okay, so then how's it different than the previous משנה
Mishna that says three
סעודות? sudot? ולא קשיא כאן לאותו חצר כאן לחצר אחרת. Velu kashya
kan le'oto hatzer kan le'hatzer acheret. Our משנה Mishna is you're bringing
it to the courtyard right in front of your house. Then you
can use as you know gather as much bread as you want.
When are you limited to three סעודות sudot for another courtyard? That
is clearly, you know, not the simple difference between the משניות, Mishnayot,
but here he's being much more lenient and saying that you can
even gather multiple loaves into one basket in certain circumstances, even if
they're not already there.
Three meals like, you know, I was going to have a few
guests at my meal?
That didn't sound like that, but that's a good interesting question about
whether you can save more than three סעודות sudot if you're planning
on having more people over. It sounds like per person that's doing
the saving. בעי רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Bai Rav Huna brei
de'Rav Yehoshua, רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב יהושע Rav
Yehoshua asked,
פריס, peiras, לפרוס, lifros, לפרוס, lifros, to spread is לפרוס, lifros, right?
Sin? פורס, poreis, right, פורס על אם שקצמן. Poreis al em shekatzman.
פריס טליתו וקיפל והניח וקיפל והניח מאי. Peiras tallito ve'kipel ve'hiniach ve'kipel
ve'hiniach mai. Let's say you spread out your טלית, tallit, okay, you
put some loaves of bread into your טלית, tallit, okay, then you
moved over to another place, you put more loaves of bread, you
went to another place, you put more loaves of bread, okay, what's
the story with that? כבא להציל דמי או כבא לקפל דמי. ke'ba
lehatzil dami o ke'ba lekapel dami. Is that like you're coming to
save, like it's all ultimately one vessel, although it is multiple puttings
of things into it, and that's okay, or is it like coming
to gather up and because and therefore it's a problem? So the
גמרא Gemara says מידאמר רבא, mide'amar Rava, so here's how he proved
it, because רבא Rava says אטייה רב שיזבי לרב חסדא ודרש. atya
Rav Shizbi le'Rav Chisda ve'darash.
So רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi misled, not intentionally, but you know, misled
רב חסדא Rav Chisda and he said the following following ברייתא baraita
relating to our משנה. Mishna. ובלבד שלא יביא כלי שהוא מחזיק יותר
מג' סעודות. U'vilvad shelo yavi kli shehu machzik yoter mi'gimel sudot. So
he said, yes, you know, you cannot when you are remember when
we spoke about the barrel breaking and putting a vessel under to
catch the dripping wine? So he clarified that statement that it's only
if the vessel is smaller than the size of three סעודות, sudot,
but if the vessel will have more wine than three סעודות, sudot,
then it's like saving more than three סעודות. sudot. So that was
the ברייתא baraita that he said and רב חסדא Rav Chisda presumably
said yeah that's a good that's a good פשט, pshat, the vessel
can't be more than three סעודות. sudot. And now so what does
this prove? Because רבא Rava said it was a mistake, אטייה atyae
he made him err, actually it could be more than three סעודות.
sudot. שמע מינה כבא להציל דמי. Shema mina ke'ba lehatzil dami. So
here you basically have a guy that's taking a large vessel putting
it under a barrel that's breaking and from רבא Rava saying that
it was a mistake you see רבא Rava says it would be
allowed if it was bigger than three סעודות sudot and he's gathering
up into this vessel more than three סעודות. sudot. So the basic
point being that if it is a single vessel even if it's
not already full and even if it's multiple putting of things in
because here the fact that the wine is dripping slowly is like
multiple of putting things in, as long as it's all coming together
in one vessel it's okay. Now there presumably there's a big difference
for letting it happen by itself and slowly dripping than going around
your house and getting all the different stuff and putting it in
the one vessel. But this is the comparison that the גמרא Gemara
makes about about that and that actually is an interesting mid-space right
between our משנה Mishna and the previous משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna
has the barrel already filled with wine, the basket already filled with
bread. The previous משנה Mishna is you're just gathering stuff around, you
know, סתם, stam, you know, different types of vessels or different loaves.
So what happens if you have the single vessel, it's all in
the end coming into one vessel, but it requires an act of
gathering. Which category is that in? And the גמרא Gemara says it
would be in the latter category, it would be okay.
So I'd have to go like fifty times in my house and
put it all in?
No, not in separate times, in one vessel to collect the get
one large vessel go all around your house, right, get
fifty loaves and put it into my...
yeah that's what the גמרא Gemara says, I agree it didn't sound
you wouldn't have thought that from the משנה Mishna but that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. שמע מינה כבא להציל דמי שמע מינה. shema
mina ke'ba lehatzil dami shema mina. ושפיר דמי. Ve'shapir dami. אמר ליה
רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא מאי טעותא, Amar lei Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak le'Rava mai tauta,
how did he know it was a mistake? Meaning maybe maybe it
is right, maybe if it's bigger than
three סעודות sudot it's not acceptable to gather stuff into it, to
put it under the wine. So מאי טעותא, mai tauta, אמר ליה
דתני ובלבד שלא יביא כלי אחר ויקלוט. amar lei de'tani u'vilvad shelo
yavi kli acher ve'yiklot. ויצרף. ve-yitzaref. Right?
Remember again when we spoke about the barrel breaking, it says as
long as you don't bring multiple vessels to gather or to not
just be directly under but to gather from the stuff that's collected,
so כלי אחר הוא דלא. kli acher hu delo. You can't bring
another vessel, אבל בההוא מנא aval behahu mana in the single vessel
that you did bring, כמה דבעי מציל kama devei matzil can be
as big as you want. So actually the גמרא Gemara is being
even taking the allowance of the משנה Mishnah and saying in the
end, even if you don't start, it doesn't start in one vessel,
but as long as you're just gathering it into one vessel, you're
okay. So again, we have these restrictions but then we have these
loopholes. ועיגול של דבילה Ve-igul shel deveilah etc. And now we get
to the fact of the loophole of come save for yourself and
then we'll figure it all out after שבת. Shabbat. So the גמרא
Gemara says חשבון מאי עבידתיה? Cheshbon mai avidtei?
Why would I make a חשבון cheshbon giving it you back and
getting paid for my effort? מפקירא זכו Mafkira zachu it's my food
now, right? You said come and take. The only way I was
allowed to take was that you were basically saying it wasn't for
you. You were relinquishing your ownership. So it's mine. The food is
presumably worth more than the effort. So אמר רב חסדא מידת חסידות
שנו כאן. Amar Rav Chisda midat chasidut shanu kan. No, no, no.
If you want to, you can keep it for yourself. We can't
demand; the only way you were allowed to save it was by
making it yours. But if you want to be a good guy,
מידת חסידות, midat chasidut, and do like the righteous thing, then you'll
give the guy his food back. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava said, חסידי אגרא דשבתא
שקלי? Chasidei agra de-Shabta shakli?
You're such a חסיד, chasid, what are you doing wanting to get
paid for working on שבת? Shabbat? You could have said what are
you doing wanting to get paid for helping this poor guy whose
house was burning down? But the גמרא Gemara also says what are
you doing trying to get paid for effort on שבת? Shabbat? You're
not supposed to get שכר שבת. sechar Shabbat. And even though technically
there it might not be שכר שבת, sechar Shabbat, you didn't ask
to be paid, you were doing it for yourself. So but still,
you even with a wink and a nod you wouldn't want to
do something that felt like being paid for effort on שבת Shabbat
if you're such a חסיד. chasid. So it can't be that you're
being so righteous. So אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather
רבא Rava says, הכא בירא שמים עסקינן. hacha bi-yerei shamayim askinan. We're
not talking about a חסיד, chasid, a חסיד chasid I should say,
not חסיד. chasid. חסיד, Chasid, somebody that is like that goes לפנים
משורת הדין lifnim mi-shurat ha-din and does
things wouldn't want to take any benefit from something that isn't. We're
talking about a ירא שמים, yerei shamayim, which means like a guy
has a strict code of morality. He doesn't want to do things
wrong, but then on the other hand, he's not going to go
out of his way to give of his own money for other
people. Like he just doesn't want to violate. Okay, ירא שמים yerei
shamayim is more like fearful than the sort of it's more the
יראה yirah than the אהבה. ahavah. Okay, so he wouldn't want to
do anything wrong. So how does that translate? So ולא ניחא ליה
דליהני מאחרים. ve-lo nicha leh de-lihani me-acherim.
He doesn't want to look take advantage of other people. Your house
was burning down and now I got myself a nice rib roast
out of it. That's inappropriate. Technically it's allowed because you made it
הפקר. hefker. But you know that's a sense of like to me
that's doing something actually wrong, benefiting from your misfortune. So on the
one hand, I don't want to benefit from your misfortune, but number
two, ובחינם נמי לא ניחא ליה דליטרח. u-ve-chinam nami lo nicha leh
de-litrach. I don't want to expend effort without getting paid for my
effort, okay? So I don't want to do anything wrong, but I'm
not such a צדיק tzaddik that I'm going to like work for
you for nothing. So it's a middle ground. And therefore והכי קאמר,
ve-hachi ka-amar, and this is what it's saying: ואם היו פקחין. ve-im
hayu pikchin. So why did it say if you were smart? Smart
somehow means
like
somehow suggests that
the you know circumvention... yeah, whatever. You know well, I mean I
think the problem with the smart is, let me just see how
רש"י Rashi explains this. The problem with the smart language is...
right. I mean smart could suggest that I'm doing it for my
own best interest. I'm being smart in terms of taking care of
my own best interest. So if I really was just concerned about
my own best interest, I would just keep the food. So what's
the language of smart? So it means smart דידעי דהאי גוונא לאו
שכר שבת הוא, de-yadi de-hai gavna lav sechar Shabbat hu, that they
know you're allowed to get paid because they know it really wasn't
שכר שבת. sechar Shabbat. You really didn't contract me, it really is
my food, I really didn't do it for you. So but if
I'm smart enough to realize that I can get paid for my
effort, עושין עמו חשבון לאחר שבת, osin imo cheshbon le-achar Shabbat, and
then it's not a problem of getting paid for work on שבת.
Shabbat. Then we can figure it out after שבת. Shabbat. So the
way the גמרא Gemara basically reads it is like this: If you
were totally doing only what you're minimally required to הלכתית, halachitit, you'd
keep it for yourself. If you were a real צדיק, tzaddik, then
you'd give it back and say you know it's your property, I
don't want anything for my effort. If you're in this middle ground
about this ירא שמים, yerei shamayim, I don't want to do anything
wrong, but on the other hand, I'd like to get paid for
my effort, then then you are actually allowed to make some arrangement
after שבת Shabbat and it's not a שכר שבת sechar Shabbat problem
because ultimately he did not explicitly contract you, ultimately you know technically
you really were doing it for yourself. So if you want to
say, look, this is now my rib roast, I'll give it back
to you if you give me a few bucks because at least
I did spend the effort, you can do it. It's not שכר
שבת. sechar Shabbat. At the end of the day, it is your
rib roast. Okay.
Why do they have to take that middle ground? What was he
trying to say by that?
No, because רש"י Rashi says because פקחין pikchin in the context probably
sounds like it means if I'm interested in my own in my
own self-interest. And if that were true, I'm just trying to make
to do what's best for me, then I would just keep the
whole
the
whole food.
I don't see why...
I think what they're trying to do is to try to encourage
this type of behavior. They're trying to say we don't expect everybody
to be a חסיד chasid and take the fruit and go to
the effort and then give it back after שבת Shabbos for nothing.
On the other hand, we hope people are, you know, nice enough
to understand what's going on and to understand that the right way
of acting here would be to save it and get paid for
your effort afterwards and you can do that in a permissible way.
I think the reason the משנה Mishna spelling it out is because
that's the behavior it's trying to encourage and thinks that people can
actually, you know, be encouraged to do. Okay, so now it goes
on. ולהיכן מצילים, U'le-heichan matzilin, where do you save it to? מאי
שנא הכא דקתני לכם? Mai shna hacha diktani lachem? Why does it-
why by the- the food, does it say save for yourselves when
it's your food? ומאי שנא הכא דקתני עמי? U'mai shna hacha diktani
imi? Why by the clothes it says save with me? So אמי
גבי מזונות קתני לכם Ami gabei mezonos katani lachem by the food
it says לכם lachem משום דלא חזו אלא ג' מזון ג' סעודות.
mishum de-lo chazu ela gimmel mazon gimmel seudos. You're only allowed to
save three meals for yourself. So therefore, if you want to save
more than three meals, they have to be saving it for themselves.
You have to give it to the other people. אבל גבי לבושים
Aval gabei levushim by clothes קתני עמי katani imi it says with
me משום דחזי ליה לכולה יומא mishum de-chazi lei le-chula yoma because
we- the משנה Mishna says that there's no limit on how many
clothes you save as long as you carry it out on your
back. Right? So by the food, I would have to say it's
your food. If you're saving it for me, I'm limited to three
meals worth. But by the clothes, I can actually take out as
many of my clothes as I want as long as they're taken
out in a permissible way. So by my clothes, I could say
help me take out my clothes by wearing them out as well.
You got the difference? Yeah? Okay, so there's a- so by the
food there's a limit if it's mine and therefore it has to
become yours. By the- by the clothes it's only how it's taken
out and it could remain mine. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan.
לובש מוציא ופושט וחוזר ולובש. Lovesh motzi u-foshet ve-chozer ve-lovesh. This is
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who argues on רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi.
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi has a very limited- wear it out, take
it out, strip it off, go in, take it out- wear it
out again. Okay. ומוציא ופושט ואפילו כל היום כולו. U-motzi u-foshet va-afillu
kol hayom kulo. You could spend the whole day doing that, wearing
it out. slow burning. Right. רבי מאיר אומר, Rebbi Meir omer, דברי
רבי מאיר. divrei Rebbi Meir. This is what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says. רבי יוסי אומר שמונה עשר כלים. Rebbi Yosi omer shmonah asar
keilim. There are only eighteen articles of clothing. ואלו הן שמונה עשר
כלים Ve-eilu hen shmonah asar keilim and these are they: מקטרון, miktron,
which is some type of like of a- of an outer cloak,
אונקלי, onkli, which is like a cape, ופונדא, u-punda, which is a-
what do I remember, what are these things? פונדא Punda is a
belt, a certain type of a- maybe outer belt. קלבבוס של פשתן,
Kalvuvus shel pishtan, a type of of some type of a linen
outer garment. וחלוק, Ve-chaluk, a shirt. ואפיליות, Ve-apilyos,
which are- trying to remember. Oh yeah, רש״י Rashi says a type
of a- a type of a head scarf.
ומעפורות, U-ma'aforot, which is- no that's the head scarf. האפיליון Ha-apilyon is
a- oh is a like- is a
cape. I think I said cape before, who knows. Okay, מעפורת ma'aforet
is a head scarf. ושני ספרקים, U-shnei safarkim, two types of like
straps, maybe to hold up your pants. ושני מנעלים, U-shnei minalim, two-
two shoes. ושני אנפליאות, U-shnei anpalyos, two socks. וביס פארגאד U-veis pargad
and two פארגאד, pargad, which is I don't know what that is.
Okay. What does it say that is anybody? Boots! Okay. וחגור שבמתניו
Ve-chagor she-bemotnav and a belt, וכובע שבראשו ve-kova she-berosho and a hat,
וסודר שבצוארו ve-sudar she-betzavaro and a handkerchief around your neck. Now you
know. Next משנה. mishna. רבי שמעון בן ננס אומר. Rebbi Shimon ben
Nanas omer. Now we get to- yes
those were the common things to
be worn in those days. Exactly. Now we get to from the
number of things we allow you to save to actually the issue
about trying to stop things from burning down and gets into important
questions about שבת Shabbat and about- like- putting out fires on שבת
Shabbat and גרמא grama on שבת Shabbat and so on. It's a
very important now discussion coming up. רבי שמעון בן ננס אומר. Rebbi
Shimon ben Nanas omer. פורסין עור של גדי על גבי שידה תיבה
ומגדל. Porsin or shel gedi al gabei shidah teivah u-migdal. You can
spread a leather- a garment of a goat, goat leather, over your
various like- you know- furniture. שאחז בה האור. She-achaz bah ha-ohr.
If the fire is on- is caught onto your let's say table,
you know, or your chest or whatever- not your whatever- your chest
of drawers, you can put this on the other part of it,
not over the fire but on the other part of it מפני
שהוא מחרך mipnei she-hu mechareich because it'll singe but it will not
burn through. So basically it's like a fireproof type of a- type
of a of a sheet. So you can spread a fireproof sheet
on your- on this furniture so that the furniture does not continue
to burn and it saves the rest of the furniture. Okay. ועושין
מחיצה בכל הכלים. Ve-osin mechitza be-chol ha-keilim. Now the other thing you
can do also to protect your stuff- if you have a fire-
is you put some vessels around it to- now presumably they- that
won't be more kindling- somehow the vessels will help contain the fire.
And now we're going to see a very particular way- the other
way? What? well that's what we're about to see. A very specific
way it'll help contain the fire. בין מלאין בין ריקנין, Bein melai'in
bein reikanin, whether they're filled or empty בשביל שלא תעבור הדליקה bishvil
she-lo ta'avor ha-dleika to prevent it. Now again, we'll get to the
filled in a minute, but presumably you could even imagine like I
don't know you just surround it with like I don't know metal
vessels or something. Some types of things that will naturally, you know,
protect and contain the fire. רבי יוסי אוסר בכלי חרס חדשים מלאים
מים. Rebbi Yosi oser be-chlei cheresh chadashim melai'im mayim. רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosi says that's fine except for pottery vessels filled with water. New
ones! New ones. Right, why? לפי שאינן יכולים לקבל את האור Lefi
she'einan yakholim lekabel et ha'or because then when the fire will cause
it to crack and the vessels will crack open and the water
will put out the fire and then you'll be indirectly putting out
the fire. So that seems like a great solution.
ומפקעים ומכבין את הדליקה. Vemipakin umakhabin et hadleika. They burst and put
out the fire. Yeah, but it sounds like that's his problem, the
Tanna Kamma isn't bothered with that and that becomes a whole issue
about גרמא Grama and indirect causation on Shabbat.
So let's see the Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav, טלית שאחזה בה האור מצד אחד. Tallit she'akhaza bah
ha'or mitzad echad. If you have a garment that the fire has
caught on one side, presumably you're not wearing this garment. נותנין עליה
מים מצד אחר. Notnin aleha mayim mitzad acher. You can put water
on the other side of the garment, basically like pour water not
on the fire but to absorb on the other side of the
clothes. Tosafot discusses why isn't that a problem about ליבון? Libun? Right,
okay, anyway, so we'll worry I don't know we won't worry about
it right now. Anyway, so now the other half of the garment
is now saturated with water
and therefore
אם כבתה כבתה Im kavta kavta and it goes out, it goes
out. So that's a way you can prevent the rest of the
garment and you're not really putting out the fire, you're just protecting
the rest of the garment and it puts itself out.
מתיב Meitiv on this, טלית שאחזה בה האור מצד אחד. Tallit she'akhaza
bah ha'or mitzad echad. If you have a tallit that has fire
caught on one side, פושטה ומתכסה בה, Poshtah umitkaseh bah, you can
take it off, put it back on, ואם כבתה כבתה, Ve'im kavta
kavta, goes out, it goes out. Now it sounds like what you're
trying to do is that the movement you're hoping will put out
the fire. Although it would seem to me it's very it would
be very contraindicated to be A, A, it could fan it, and
B, to be putting on a tallis that's burning. So I don't
know about any of that, but somehow it's felt that that was
some way indirectly. The other obvious problem here is that like it's
a little funny, like nobody would think to really suggest this even
if it would be effective because it's like a it's not a
real אינו מתכוין. Eino Mitkaven. It's like an אינו מתכוין Eino Mitkaven
with like a wink, right? Oh, I'm just trying to put my
garment on, and here all along what you're really hoping is that
the act of putting it on is going to cause the fire
to go out. So it's not a very much of an אינו
מתכוין. Eino Mitkaven. Deep down you're trying to get that to happen.
So you know it's not exactly clear to me at all why
that is allowed. וכן ספר תורה שאחזה בו האור, Vekhein Sefer Torah
she'akhaza bo ha'or, similarly if a Sefer Torah caught fire, פושטו וקורא
בו, Poshto vekorei bo, you can open it up and read from
it ואם כבתה כבתה Ve'im kavta kavta and it goes out, it
goes out. Again maybe I don't know somehow by opening it you're
you're exposing it to air and I don't know air usually makes
fires continue to burn. Anyway, besides that I don't understand how it's
practically effective, I don't understand why that's even a solution because it
seems to me that's like not much of an אינו מתכוין. Eino
Mitkaven.
But anyway yes it did you mean to say any like פסיק
רישא Pesiq Resha issues with that and just you know?
That's true, but even without פסיק רישא, Pesiq Resha,
it's a מתכוין, Mitkaven, like you're hoping that this will happen, you
know. Now again maybe it's going to happen but it's still a
גרמא. Grama. You're opening it up and then the elements somehow are
putting it out. But anyway even that's not so clear. It sounds
some way the opening is part of what, I don't know, it's
not clear to me at all. Anyway, so the question is why
did they say that? Why doesn't it say, you know, why doesn't
it talk about like I mean it seems like you can't actually
actively like put liquid or put some cover on it to protect
it. כמאן דאמר כרבי שמעון בן ננס. Kiman de'amar keRabbi Shimon ben
Nanos. Oh, you know why? Because he says like Rabbi Shimon ben
Nanos. Rabbi Shimon ben Nanos is the one that says you can
actively put a קטברא Katavra a cover and a protector. That would
be like the water. This ברייתא Baraita presumably would rather you not
actively do some you know protect it, just use it naturally and
hope that it goes out through natural use, but not actively put
a protector. So the Gemara says, אימא דאמר רבי שמעון בן ננס
משום דמחרך. Aima de'amar Rabbi Shimon ben Nanos mishum de'makhrekh. One minute,
Rabbi Shimon ben Nanos says that's okay if it just singes this
fireproof garment that you've put on top. גרם כיבוי מי אמר? Geram
kibbuy mi amar? But if you saturate with water, that actually is
not just going to protect, it's going to cause the fire to
go out. Whoever allowed you to indirectly cause it to go out?
So the Gemara says, אין, In, yes he does allow it. מדקתני
סיפא, Mideka tani seifa, since the end of the Mishnah says, רבי
יוסי אוסר בכלי חרס חדשים מלאים מים שאינן יכולים לקבל את האור
והן מפקעין ומכבין את הדליקה, Rabbi Yosi oser bikhlei cheres chadashim mel'eim
mayim she'einan yakholim lekabel et ha'or ve'hen mipakin umakhabin et hadleika, since
Rabbi Yosi forbids with the vessels filled with water which are going
to burst and put it out, מכלל, Mikhlal, from that you can
infer דתנא קמא שרי, deTanna Kamma sharei, that the first opinion says
that's okay. So even if it causes it to go out. So
in the same way you can have a vessel filled with water,
you can saturate one end of the garment with water and it'll
put itself out. That is גרם כיבוי, Geram kibbuy, indirect extinguish. Which
again, since the Gemara assumes that גרם כיבוי Geram kibbuy is a
problem, it sounds like it's assuming about reading the Sefer Torah or
taking the garment on and off is not somehow indirectly causing it
to extinguish. So then what's it saying? I mean, I don't get
it at all. Then what's the point of saying it if it's
not somehow helping in the process? So I don't know how to
deal with that case at all about reading the Sefer Torah or
putting the garment on and off, but the basic point is Tanna
Kamma of our Mishnah holds if it's indirect you can put water
around it basically and it'll come and put itself out or you
know saturate the garment with the water, put the water in the
vessels. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, yes.
Is this the Gemara that's used to justify things like... Is this
the גמרא Gemara that's used to justify things like שבת Shabbat mode
ovens and things like that?
Yeah,
in a way. That's a little bit different than גרמא, grama, but
yeah, it's part of this discussion. I mean a lot of, you
know, all the what do you call it? The, you know, what's
that place called? The צומת Tzomet devices all use this idea of
doing things not slightly indirectly and so on. Right. So this is
a very important גמרא Gemara about that. And the question is, okay,
so גרמא grama is allowed, but under what circumstances to save your
house from burning down? Is it allowed סתם? stam? What's the threshold
and so on? תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We taught, נר שעל גבי
טבלה ner she'al gabei tavla if you have a lamp on top
of a table, like a whatever,
tableau, table, whatever, מנער את הטבלה והוא נופל, menayer et hatavla vehu
nofel, ואם כבתה כבתה. v'im kavta kavta.
Basically, presumably you don't even have a fire, but basically what you're
doing here is like
you want to, you know, I don't know, let's say you've got
your candles on your, your, you know what's it called, your candle
plate, what's that thing called, whatever, לעכטער, lechter, that's what I was
going to say. Anyway, so basically you can say, oh, you know
what? And it's still burning. You can say, oh, I actually want
to go ahead and I want to wash the candle plate, the
לעכטער, lechter, so you take it out and the lamp and the
candles fall down, the גמרא Gemara will get to that, the candles
fall down, you go, you wash it, and if the fact that
they fell down now causes them to burn out, fine, that's not
your problem. Now again, my question is are you trying to get
them to burn out? And then if you're trying to get them
to burn out, why isn't it your problem? Why won't we say
that it's basically if that was your attempt, it's a type of
a מתכוין? mitkaven? Just because ostensibly you're doing another act, again, as
long as if this is a desired end result that you desire,
it's similar to the case before about the reading of the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah and the garment. And I have to tell you,
you know, if you're trying to do this, I don't get why
because you're ostensibly doing something else that that makes this permissible. So
maybe you're not trying, maybe you just you literally just want to
take the טבלה tavla and you don't have to worry about the
fact that they'll go, that they'll put themselves out. So anyway, let's
see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי,
Amrei d'vei Rabbi Yannai, they said in the house of Rabbi Yannai,
לא שנו אלא בשוכח, lo shanu ela beshoche'ach, it's only if you
forgot and left a lamp on that plate, אבל במניח, aval bemani'ach,
if you intentionally left the lamp on the plate, like Michael says,
נעשה בסיס לדבר אסור, na'aseh basis ledavar asur, then the plate is
defined as a base support for that and the base becomes מוקצה.
muktzeh. תנן, Tnan, נר שאחורי הדלת, ner she'achorei hadelet, if you have
a lamp that is behind the door, פותח ונועל כדרכו, pote'ach veno'el
kedarko, you can open and close the door as you would, ואם
כבתה כבתה. v'im kavta kavta. Now here it seems clear that this
is not your intention. It's a question about can I walk into
my house if there's candles burning inside and by opening and closing
the door, that might cause the candles to go out. So this
is a case where you're not trying to do it, which I
think would be the best way to read the earlier cases as
well because as I said if you're trying I don't get about
the whole כוונה kavana issue. So you're not trying to do it
and the thing is you don't have to worry, you're not intending,
it's not a פסיק רישא, psik reisha, you're not,
and therefore if it goes out, it goes out, you can go
in and out of the door. So לייט עליה רב, Lait alei
Rav, Rav cursed at this type of a person that would do
that or this
statement. אמרי לה רבינא לרב Amreilah Ravina leRav אחא בריה דרבא, Acha
brei deRava, ואמרי לה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, ve'amrei lah
Rav Acha brei deRava leRav Ashi, מאי טעמא לייט ליה רב, mai
ta'ama lait lei Rav, why did Rav curse, curse that? אילימא משום
דרב סבר לה כרבי יהודה, Eileima mishum deRav savar lah k'Rabbi Yehuda,
Rav holds like Rabbi Yehuda that אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven is אסור,
asur, and this is an אינו מתכוין eino mitkaven because it might
go out, ותנא תנא לה כרבי שמעון, veTanna tana lah k'Rabbi Shimon,
and the תנא Tanna held like Rabbi Shimon. So משום דרב סבר
לה כרבי יהודה, mishum deRav savar lah k'Rabbi Yehuda, just because Rav
holds like Rabbi Yehuda, כל דתני רבי שמעון מיליט לייט, kol detani
Rabbi Shimon meilit lait, he's going to curse anybody that teaches something
like Rabbi Shimon? So it's a total unreasonable position that אינו מתכוין
eino mitkaven you can open the door even if it causes some
of the some burning. So I mean might cause it to extinguish,
it's אינו מתכוין. eino mitkaven. אמרי ליה, Amri lei, he said back,
no, בהא אפילו רבי שמעון מודה, beha afilu Rabbi Shimon modeh, even
Rabbi Shimon would agree that this is a problem. Why? אביי ורבא
Abaye v'Rava דאמרי תרוייהו, de'amri tarvaihu, like we say
Abaye and Rava say, מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות, modeh
Rabbi Shimon b'psik reisha velo yamut, Rabbi Shimon agrees if you cut
off a head it won't die. So here if the candle is
right near the door and by opening it, it automatically causes the,
you know, the thing to go out a little bit to slow
the burning or affect the burning, then that really should be a
problem, that should be a פסיק רישא. psik reisha.
So that would be different than putting the water on it because
you're not on the other end.
This is like directly you're opening the door. Now again, here it
says that it actually causes it to go out. So the question
becomes, you know, not just how it affects the burning. So the
question really is is it a real פסיק רישא psik reisha that
it goes out? That that it would definitely go out? And this
leads some אחרונים achronim to develop a concept
called, called קרוב לפסיק רישא, karov lipsik reisha, which is pretty funny.
I mean פסיק רישא psik reisha means definite, you know, but okay,
highly likely. And then there becomes this category called highly likely which
also becomes problematic or not. So that's a very interesting גמרא Gemara
in the discussions of פסיק רישא. psik reisha. Okay, but the good
thing I should say about the questions I raised earlier is that
it seems at least in this case the גמרא, Gemara, the assumption
is you don't want it to go out, that's not your intention.
And that would help understand some of the earlier cases as well
if ממש mamash it was not your intention for it to go
out as opposed to... Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara just to
finish this point, אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda פותח אדם דלת
כנגד מדורה בשבת. poteach adam delet kneged medura beShabbat. That maybe it's
a candle, it's a single lamp, but if you've got like a
bonfire going, no problem opening the door, because it won't make it
go out. So לייטי ליה אביי, laite leh Abaye, אביי Abaye
questioned, במאי עסקינן, bemai askinan, what are you talking about? אילימא ברוח
מצויה, eileima beruach metzuya, if you're talking about that it's a common
wind, meaning a normal, calm type of a wind, מאי טעמא דמאן
דאסר, mai taama deman de’assar, who would ever say it’s forbidden? Right?
Of course, a normal wind isn’t going to impact a nice burning
fire. אי ברוח שאינה מצויה, ei beruach she’eina metzuya,
if it’s a strong wind, like a storm wind or something, מאי
טעמא דמאן דשרי, mai taama deman desharei, why should anybody allow it
if it will likely put out the fire? Does it mean פסיק
רישא, pesik reisha, does it mean likely? But anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says לעולם ברוח מצויה, le’olam beruach metzuya, really it’s a normal wind.
מר סבר גזרינן, mar savar gazrinan, one says we make a גזירה
gezeira that we don’t even allow you to do it by a
normal wind because then you won’t be paying attention, and then when
it’s a highly windy outside you’ll come to open it and it’ll
blow it out. ומר סבר לא גזרינן umar savar lo gazrinan and
the other say no, we’re not concerned about that. When it’s a
strong wind and you know opening the door will put out the
fire, then you’ll be careful, but we don’t make, we’re not concerned
about other cases. Anyway, from this גמרא, Gemara, from this does develop
this issue about do we take cases that פסיק רישא pesik reisha
is a problem and say not only is פסיק רישא pesik reisha
a problem but something that’s highly likely or we’re going to make
a גזירה gezeira that it’ll lead to פסיק רישא? pesik reisha? There
is some discussion of אחרונים Acharonim around these cases. Okay, so we
will continue with גרם כיבוי Geram Kibuy tomorrow.
So can I open the door if it’s a רוח שמצויה ruach
shemetzuya that won’t necessarily put it out?